welcome welcome to meditating with genre
Viki this is a course it's a progressive
course in which I will teach you a set
of skills that will build on each other
over time on Monday and Thursdays at
9:30 the teaching days that's when I'll
teach you a new skill we'll go through
an exercise together Tuesdays and
Wednesdays and Fridays and Saturdays and
this is one of those days we will meet
together I will do a quick review of the
most recent principle I've taught and
then we will sit together and B will be
a question and answer period at the end
in fact after every sitting will be
about a 10-minute Q&A period so as I
said on John rebecky I'm a cognitive
psychologist and a cognitive scientist
at the University of Toronto I study
mindfulness and related phenomena like
flow and mystical them academically
scientifically I run experiments etc but
I'm also a practitioner I've been
practicing the past na and meta and Tai
Chi Chuan for 29 years and teaching it
professionally for close to 20 years so
I first of all want to remember to thank
you all for joining me and I also want
to thank my TAC support amar who will be
handling questions you might be asking
throughout and I'm always deeply
grateful for his support and my beloved
son is Jason is also helping me out on a
daily basis so I want to say thanks to
both of them okay so what we've talked
about last time is we talked about
finding your Center and we talked about
three aspects of it if you are joining
us for the first time I recommend you go
back to the previous video where I
instruct more in detail how to find your
Center and then you could watch this
video a little bit later and that way
you can get into proper progressive
sequence but a quick review for all of
us we find our Center
surely remember back and forth so I
decide the head we sink into a cigarette
center by relaxing all of our muscles by
opening a chest muscles and I've been
with muscle stomach muscles we savor our
Center by creating a felt memory of what
it's like so that we can find our way
back and we centre our attention by
stepping back and looking at our
sensations rather than automatically
looking through the patterns and
processes in our mind we label others
when were distracted we label the
distracting process we don't get
involved with the content we label the
distracting process with an ing word
excuse me thinking imagining wandering
listening etc and then we return our
attention to the breath and that's where
we train our attitude we're centering
our attitude
we're neither fighting nor feeding our
monkey mind because throughout all of
this
we are attempting to the friend
ourselves so we're going to sit again in
a couple of minutes make sure he's got
some comfortable clothing on make sure
you've got as we talked about last time
you have your loft see I'm sitting on a
pillow because I want to get my knees
level or if possible below my hips some
of you may find it easier to sit on the
edge of your pillow right cross-legged
because this is a little bit more
demanding on the legs if you can do this
though that this is good because it
tends to keep the pelvis less
lateralized remember also that although
you should experiment with your posture
you're not going to find a perfect
posture that makes you free of all
discomfort well you've done up your legs
might fall asleep you might get some you
know achiness in your legs
things like that however you shouldn't
have a stabbing or burning pain in your
back if not is happening for you go
through the centering exercise if you're
in a chair and then lean back to get
that little bit of support from the back
of the chair or what some people do in
my meditation classes is they sit right
next to a wall they go through the
centering exercise and then they lean a
little bit back onto a wall
take some pressure off their back
alright so like I said I will be taking
some questions at the end after we've
sat for a bit and we have some questions
also held over from yesterday I'll
address those ones first and then any of
the new questions coming in all right so
please prepare yourself and we will
start to sit together please begin to
meditate
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can to
integrate what you cultivated in your
practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition meditation
is not a vacation it's an education for
transformation so let's take some
questions right here
they have a question from crema should
we be focusing on our breath either the
tip of the nose or the belly yes you're
definitely focusing on your breath I
would recommend focusing there are
traditions that focus on the breath of
the tip of the nose but the tradition
I'm teaching a tradition that integrates
for pasta and meta and touch each one is
one that puts an emphasis on the don t
and also known as the Hara and so
following your breath in your abdomen
well the reason why I recommend this and
you both pick one and stick with it
though is that by focusing on the breath
and in the abdomen it tends to keep your
breathing closer to your center of
gravity and it adds to your sense of
stability and groundedness this tends to
keep our focus more up in the head area
and this is a little bit more heady a
little bit more eccentric this is more
you know earth centric grounding and
it's actually closer to your center of
gravity so I recommend following your
breath in your don't am can you talk
about detailed posture what kind of
pillow is this any easy substitute so
this is called a Asif ooh easy
substitute are hard but Jason could you
pass me also the meditation bench please
so you can order these this is a
meditation bench I'm letting my son use
it and it's very portable and then you
sit on this there's various meditation
benches you can order of course in our
current situation ordering things is
difficult
you might want to get something that's
got a fairly substantial solidity to it
and then put a pillow over top of it a
regular pillow in order to get some of
the stability from with regular pillows
as they tend to crush with time and that
tends to uproot people that sort of
disturb their meditation posture so if
you can put something like like a small
box or a small stool and and then put a
pillow over that that might work as as a
transitional thing when you get a chance
and I understand our current
circumstances but getting us a food
which is a specific meditation pillow or
portable or a non portable meditation
Vince is actually optimal is this the
pasta yes it's a kind of a pasta it is a
form of a pasta that has come through on
in one so there's sort of a set of
influences there's you know the pasta
activating the pasta it was brought to
North America by Goldstein and cornfield
and others Ted in insurance and then I
was taught this in conjunction with
Metta and with Tai Chi Chuan and in a
toilet and some chicken in a highly
inter penetrating manner I also learned
a mindfulness healing art I've got
professional training at I practiced for
about a decade as a shelter therapist so
all of that is going into it and then
also a huge important influence is all
the work I've done on mindfulness
Insight flow etc that's also informing
how I'm teaching you what do you do with
the thought inside question oh I'm sorry
I should have mentioned that the second
question about the pillow was from
harina Destin thank you
the third question was also for from
crimina and this is from saga 20 what to
do with the thought which is insight
question the teacher that you want to
remember better to write it away write
it right away
or get back to
breath and let it come back continuously
I recommend not breaking your meditation
to write it down
I recommend labeling it as thinking and
returning to your breath and be willing
to let your insight go and have faith
and trust
spontaneous aspects of your mind will
give you your insight or question back
to you once you come out with time that
will become very very regular for you
you'll have a on the inside or thought
in the meditation you'll let it go
completely you'll be able to return to
the breath you'll think it's for that
you'll come back you'll say oh I had
some sort of insight and then it comes
back this especially you can train
yourself to say if you put a book near
you and say during the meditation I'm
not going to try to hold onto my
insights but as soon as I come out of
the meditation I will try to remember
this and so I recommend that as a
strategy who's behind me this way Jason
is behind me that way on my son and
there's nothing no one behind me right
now is it okay to recenter the body
during a meditation set if I feel like
I'm slouching over yes it's a good idea
to slightly readjust do those micro
adjustments to recover your Center that
is completely fine to do I find it
difficult to constantly do that was from
Lars Karl max wraps oh ho I'll get
better remember to mention your names
please forgive me asked who's behind me
anastasiya terekhova is asking I find it
difficult to constantly do baby breath
and find myself having to take a really
deep breath through my chest is this
just from being unaccustomed to belly
breathing yes it is and I recommend that
if don't force the baby breathing at all
I just let it go if you're breathing is
up here then follow it there try to keep
your chest open and your shoulders down
follow your breathing here and then you
know see if you can very gently coax it
a little bit little tiny bit each time
but not force it especially don't get
into the hop
taking lots of deep breaths or you're
going to hyperventilate so the baby
breathing for some people because we've
got lots of just breathing it takes time
and so the baby breathing is a goal you
are gradually very very gradually
working your way towards okay follow
your breath where it naturally is even
if it's very high and then keep it in
mind that you're going to try and open
up and let it sort of melt and dissolve
and drain down and over time it'll drop
into your belly you'll be able to do
more baby breathing this is from mr.
clear do you exhale from the belly first
or the upper lungs so I generally exhale
from the belly first and then on the
upper lungs
I tend if I'm exhaling here that tends
to sort of choke it off from the excel
so here and then exhale here and then
you follow the breath coming up there's
Chicana exercises and pranayama
exercises in fact where you're following
the breath in just that manner are there
any more questions that we need to
address I think that's it
and so we're also at the end of our time
and it's been wonderful to sit with you
I want to remind you that I will be here
again tomorrow at 30 I will go a little
bit longer tomorrow usually we'll go 40
minutes because Thursday's a teaching
class and tomorrow I'm going to teach
you how to find a second thing of your
core for I'm going to teach you how to
find your route remember
continuity of practice is more important
than quantity try to sit for at least 15
minutes but if you can honestly only sit
for five please sit for five thank you
very much keep up with your practice and
if I didn't get to your questions
I promise we'll get to them tomorrow
take good care everyone thank you for
your time and attention and thank you
again to amar and to Jason